Guide to the Ambrose Bierce Papers, 1872-1913
Department of Special Collections
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bryan, W.J. To Phelan, James, Jul 9 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - [Clouse? Nell?] To Christiansen, Carrie, Mar 10 1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Christiansen, Carrie To Neale, Walter, Jan 31 1915 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Crawford, Julia To Cowden, Helen[Bierce], Nov 15 1915 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Francillon, R.E. To Gowing, Richard, Apr 8 1875 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Gowing, Richard To Sampson, H., Mar 3 1875 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Neale, H.S. To Christiansen, Carrie (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Nov 12 1913
      - Dec 15 1913
      - Dec 15 1914
      - Mar 15 1915
    - Neale, Walter (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - To Attorney for the U.S., Jul 7 1911
      - To CHATTO & WIINDUS, Oct 6 1908
      - To Christiansen, Carrie
        - Oct 31 1911
        - Nov 2 1911
        - Nov 8 1911
        - Jan 10 1914
        - Jun 2 1914
        - Jul 3 1914
        - Sept 10 1914
        - Jun 15 1915
      - To Cotton, Lella, Oct 6 1908; Jun 17 1909
      - To Cowden, Helen[Bierce], Dec 7 1916
      - To Franklin, Milton W. n.d.[letter is in Neale's letters to Bierce, Box 2, folder 10]
      - To Howes, S.O., Aug 4 1908
      - To Jackson, Stuart, Jun 19 1911
      - To James, U.P., Sept 2 1909
      - To Kaufman, Edward S., Oct 4 1911
      - To New York Times Company, Jul 25 1911
      - To Petersen, John, Oct 7 1908
      - To Pollard, Percival, Jan 26 1909; Jun 27 1911
      - To Richards, Grant, Jul 3 1914
      - To Scheffauer, Herman, Oct 12 1909
      - To Stephens, A.G., Jan 16 1912
    - Schulte, F.J. To Danziger, G.A., Aug 4 1892; [Feb 13] 1893 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Sinclair, Upton To Sterling, George, Sept 10 1908 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Starrett, Vincent (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - To Christiansen, Carrie, Mar 18 1918
      - To Cowden, Helen [Bierce]
        - Nov 12 1917
        - Jan 20 1918
        - Aug 12 1918
    - [Suman?] H.B. To[Crumpacker?] Edgar, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Taylor, [?] W. To Lynch, Jeremiah, Jan 21 1889 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Wagner, Madge Morris To Atherton, Gertrude, Mar 10 1893 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Wilkinson, Warring To Walsh, Miss [Lilly], Jul 2 1895; Jul 25 1895 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified correspondence (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Fragments of correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
- SERIES II: LEGAL DOCUMENTS & BUSINESS CONTRACTS
  - 1838Deposition
  - April 30, 1872Passport
  - December 7, 1892Wells, Fargo & Co. Receipt (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - April 3, 1893F.J. Schulte & Co. bill (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - May 18, 1901Contract Agreement
  - April 7, 1903Copyright Agreement
  - September 29, 1910National Metropolitan Bank of Washington loan agreement (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - May 15, 1909Contract Agreement
  - June 6, 1914Union Trust Company safe renewal (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - December 14Invoice, St. Helena Public Cemetery Association (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - April 4, 1916Union Trust Company authorization (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - n.d.Neale Publishing Company Proxy (Box 3, Folder 1)
- SERIES III: OTHER PERSONAL PAPERS
  - Four address books (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - One address book (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Two billfolds (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clippings case (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings case (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Diary (not in A.B.'s hand); see note from Paul Fatout; Correspondence File, April 1945. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous AB Materials (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Royal Mail Steam Packet Company (ship's detail)
- SERIES IV: PAPERS ABOUT BIERCE
  - Notes on Bierce by Paul Jordan Smith (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes on Bierce by Paul Jordan Smith (Box 3, Folder 10)
- SERIES V: MISCELLANEOUS PRINTED MATERIALS
  - May 23, 1928clipping: "Tells New Version of Bierce's Death" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - n.d.clipping: "Bierce Fate Inquiry Begun" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - n.d.clipping: "A Tender and the Response" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - n.d.clipping: "Ambrose Bierce" [hand detail] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Proceedings of the Twenty-Third Annual Reunion Ninth Regiment Indiana Volunteer Infantry Association (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Proceedings of the Twenty-Fifth Annual Reunion Ninth Regiment Indiana Volunteer Infantry Association October 6-7, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Recollections of the Chickamauga Campaign by Henry S. Foote (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings Scrapbook
  - Bierce columns from the New York American and Journal, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Provenance
    Gift of Mr. Elken Osher, 1982
    - 29 March 1902:"Little Johnny on the Toady"
    - 8 April 1902:"For the Canal"
    - 10 April 1902:"Little Johnny on the Sheep"
    - 15 April 1902:"Little Johnny on the Tootsy Wootsy"
    - 16 April 1902:"For Secretary of Something"
    - 2 May 1902:"Little Johnny on More Tigers"
    - 12 May 1902:"Little Johnny on the Soldier"
    - 14 May 1902:"The Melancholy Author"
    - 5 June 1902:"An Unconquered Editor"
    - 7 June 1902:"The Struggle Between Man and Dog"
- SERIES VI: SKETCHES
  - "Those Dear Boys" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Baked Beans" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pen & Ink, written on reverse by Helen Bierce Cowden (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Ye Dishwashing" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "My New Girl" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Pen & Ink Sketch by Leigh Bierce"
  - "Ambrose Bierce"
  - Ambrose Bierce's Civil War Sketchbook (Box 4, Folder 2)
- SERIES VII: PHOTOGRAPHS
  Each item is listed by original accession number, some identifications are in Helen Bierce's hand. All identifications of AB as "Pops" were made by AB's daughter, Helen.
  - M2485 Photo Postcard with Bierce & Neale Family, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2516 Reproduction of Sketch of Bierce, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2517 [missing] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2518 Photograph: Leigh Bierce, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2519 Photograph: D.C. Patterson "[near] Atlanta, Geo., Sept. 1864" Photographer: A.S. Morse. Nashville, Tenn., Sept 1864 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2520 Photograph: Laura Gettiffe. Opposition Photographic Gallery, S.F., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2521 Ambrose Bierce on a pier with friend [unidentified], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2522 Ambrose Bierce at Percival Pollard's home., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2523 Ambrose Bierce at Percival Pollard's home., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2524 Cat on stairs, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2525 Ambrose Bierce at Percival Pollard's home., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2525a Photograph Reproduction of M2525 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2526 Albert Bierce at the Russian River. "Grizzly, taken at his shack, Guerneville. Russian River.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2527 Photograph: "Ambrose Bierce and Christiansen girls Laura & Carrie, his secretary.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2528 Photograph: Helen Bierce. "Helen B. St. Helena, California.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2529 Photograph: Day Bierce as a Child. Photographer: Netterville Briggs. Leamington, London., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2530 Photograph: Laura Gettiffs. "Laura Gettiffs. "Nosey." San Rafael. Cosmopolitan Gallery. SF., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2531 Photograph: Fred J. Bierce, n.d., 1" x 1 1/4" (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2532 Photograph: "Kitty Miles and Ambrose Bierce." (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2533 Photograph: "Ambrose & Laila Cotten.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2534 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce on a pier with friend [unidentified], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2535 Photograph: "Percival Pollard & Guests" including Ambrose Bierce, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2536 Photograph: "Bierce & Sterling.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2537 Photograph: A Bierce with Walter Neale and seated women., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2537a Photograph reproduction of M2536 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2538 Tintype: Leigh Bierce, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2539 Tintype: Ambrose Bierce and [Leigh Bierce], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2540 Photograph: "Ambrose Bierce & 'Jo'.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2541 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce with pet squirrel in Washington, D.C. (duplicate), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2542 Photograph: "Ambrose Bierce & Miss Christiansen. Rock Spring Club, Virginia. Atlantic Photo Gallery. Coney Island, N.Y., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2543 Photograph: House at Russian River. Figure unidentified., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2544 Photograph: "9th Ind[iana Infantry] Officer." Signed., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2545 Photograph: "Col. Blake, 9th Ind." Walter & Heuck's Gallery., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2546 Photograph: Signed "Yours faithfully, Walter Blackburn Harte. 1893." Photographer: F. Waldon Smith. Boston, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2547 Photograph: A. Bierce. [Albert] "Dear Old Sloots, taken in our back yard.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2547a Photograph reproduction of M2547 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2548 Photograph: "Ralph Smith. Physician." Lainer Instantaneous Photos. SF., [1887] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2549 Photograph: "Walter Neale & family with Major Bierce.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2550 Photograph: A Bierce and Three Women on steps. "Reform at [?] Dr. Doyle & family." Mar 28 1898 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2550a-b Photograph reproductions of M2550 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2551 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and George Herman Scheffauer., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2552 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and company of friends., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2553 Photograph: Albert S. Bierce "Taken in back yard of house in Berkeley.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2554 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce's brother and nephew: "A[lbert] S. Bierce, C[arleton] A. Bierce, his son.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2554a Photograph reproduction of M2554 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2555 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce. "Apollo Belvedere.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2556 Photograph: Josephine Clifford McCrackin. "Joe[sie] McCracken at the ruins of her house.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2557 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and Josephine McCrackin. "Pops & Jo." [AB], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2558 Photograph: Squirrel. [Washington, D.C.], n.d. [circa 1900] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2559 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce with pet squirrel in Washington, D.C., n.d. [circa 1900] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - M2560 Photograph: "Pops and his pet squirrel taken at the Olympia.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2561 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce & pet squirrel, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2562 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and pet squirrel "Washington, D.C.", n.d.[circa 1900-1913] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2563 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and pet squirrel "Taken at the Smithsonian Grounds. Washington, D.C.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2564 Photograph: "Walter Neale, Mrs. Neale, Ambrose Bierce, Neale children. Taken at Bensonhurst." May 1911 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2565 Photograph: "Cotten Girls, Herman 'Sheff' [George Herman Scheffauer], Ambrose Bierce.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2566 Photograph: [Ambrose Bierce, Julie & Kitty Miles] "Wright's.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2567 Photograph: Store House. Bull Run Battlefield. (mounted with printed description) On Front: "Virginia, April 5, 1907." Apr 5 1907 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2568 Photo Post Card (not used), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2569 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce. Signed with message: "Mrs. D.S. Hirshberg. With compliments of Ambrose Bierce." Photographer: Elite Studio. H.H. Slakesly. St. Helena, Cal., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2569a Photograph reproduction of M2569 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2570 Photograph: Albert S. Bierce. "Grizzley." Photographer: Haussler. San Jose. Oakland., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2570a-b Photograph reproduction of M2570 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2571 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce, George Herman Scheffauer, and [Julie Miles]., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2572 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and three women beneath the flag. [K. Miles, Christiansen, A.B., J. Miles], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2573 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2574 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce and friends. (unidentified), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2574a-b Photograph reproductions of M2574 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2575 Photograph: "Ambrose Bierce, Julie Miles Kitty Miles, Herman Scheffauer. Los Gatos. Apr 3, '99." Apr 3 1899 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2576 Photograph: "Pops, Julie, Sheff."* Julie's Brother at Los Gatos.", n.d. [Apr 1899] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M2577 Photograph: Signed: "Yours faithfully, Walter Blackburn Harte. Boston, Mass, 1895." Reverse side: "To Ambrose Bierce, whom I am-proud to be able to number among my friends. W.B. Harte. 18 March/95. Photographer: The Royal Studio, Boston, Mass., Mar 18, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2577a Photograph reproduction of M2577 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2578 Photograph: Interior of house. "Amy Wells' Being Alone.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2579 Photograph: Doyle [Dr. Charles William Doyle] & family & friend, Ambrose Bierce. [Jove] Cal., Oct 1898." Oct 1898 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2580 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce. Reverse side lower right: "Bessie B. Yates.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2581 Photograph: Albert S. Bierce. Signed: "Yours truly. A.S. Bierce.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2582 Photograph: Helen Bierce. "Helen Bierce in Carson, Nevada with gift from father.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2583 Photograph: countryside with horse-drawn buggy. unidentified., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2584 Photo from Pacific Photo Journal Sept 1899. "Ambrose Bierce in his den." Photo by H. Scheffauer. 1899 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2585 Photograph: Mrs. McCrackin., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2586 Photograph: "Wright's." Reverse side lower right: "Bessie B. Yates.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2587 Photograph: "Leigh Bierce when with Art Dept. in Hearst's New York Paper.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2588 Photograph: R. G. Ingersoll., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2589 Photograph: "Room at Wright's" Reverse side lower right: "Bessie B. Yates.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2590 Photograph: "Ambrose Bierce & his "little sweetheart" who upon being asked what she & Ambrose were doing said "O, me & Ambrose was kissing behind the door." (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - M2591 Photograph: "Leigh's Hands.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2592 Photograph: "Wright's. Reverse side lower right: "Bessie B. Yates.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2593 Photograph: Winter scene. Inn near Mount Lowe., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2594. Photograph: Winter scene: Inn near Mount Lowe. alternate view., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2595 Photograph: Smoking volcano, unidentified, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2596 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2597 Photograph: "Helen Bierce Cowden's house in Bloomington, Illinois, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2598 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce seated. Signed: "For Carrie Christiansen. Ambrose Bierce. Englewood, N.J. July 23, 1896." Photographer: Prinee. Wash., D.C. Jul 23 1896 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2598a Photograph reproduction of M2598 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2599 Photograph: Band with [Leigh Bierce's] picture circled. Lower right: "Before." Reverse: "Oct 23 1892. St. Helena. Hunt's Grove. Sunday eve." Photographer: Elite Studio. H.H. Blakesly. St. Helena, Cal. Oct 23 1892 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2600 Photograph: "Hotel at Los Gatos. Los Gatos. June 1898." Reverse side lower right. "Bessie B. Yates." Jun 1898 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2601 Photograph: Birds in Flight. "From Edwin Arnold in Japan." Reverse side lower right: "Omnia vincit Amor.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2594. Photograph: Winter scene: Inn near Mount Lowe. alternate view., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2595 Photograph: Smoking volcano, unidentified, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2596 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2597 Photograph: "Helen Bierce Cowden's house in Bloomington, Illinois, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2598 Photograph: Ambrose Bierce seated. Signed: "For Carrie Christiansen. Ambrose Bierce. Englewood, N.J. July 23, 1896." Photographer: Prinee. Wash., D.C. Jul 23 1896 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2598a Photograph reproduction of M2598 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2599 Photograph: Band with [Leigh Bierce's] picture circled. Lower right: "Before." Reverse: "Oct 23 1892. St. Helena. Hunt's Grove. Sunday eve." Photographer: Elite Studio. H.H. Blakesly. St. Helena, Cal. Oct 23 1892 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2600 Photograph: "Hotel at Los Gatos. Los Gatos. June 1898." Reverse side lower right. "Bessie B. Yates." Jun 1898 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M2601 Photograph: Birds in Flight. "From Edwin Arnold in Japan." Reverse side lower right: "Omnia vincit Amor.", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M4148 Photograph: "For Mr. Neale., Ambrose Bierce -- as he was in 1896." 1896 (Box 4, Folder 6)